[leaves crunching]
[Eun and Seomseom panting]
My lady. [gasps]
[sinister music playing]
My lady, we have to get moving.
We're all going to die
if you waste time here.
We have to move forward, my lady.
We have to hurry!
[soldier] Find Choi's daughter!
[pants and whispers]
My lady, hurry. Hurry.
-[gasps]
-[soldier 1] Search everywhere.
[Seomseom] They're after you.
-[soldier 1] This way!
-We're blocked off.
We're completely surrounded.
[soldier 2] She can't have gone far.
Find them now!
The path to the outskirts is blocked.
There's no way we can get past them.
What do we do?
My lady!
You have to pull yourself together.
If we get caught here,
then both of us will get killed.
-Officer Jung.
-What?
He said if I was ever in trouble,
Mapo's Forefinger would help us.
We need to find him.
We'll find out where he is together.
[breathing heavily] All right. This way.
[both panting]
[sighs wearily]
[boatman] What are you going to do?
The sun will rise soon.
Chief Kang.
Listen, if I'm not there on time,
you must go alone.
My lord.
All of our lives depend on the map,
making it safely.
I'm counting on you.
We have to go.
Oh, over there.
[breath trembling]
[both panting]
[sinister music playing]
-[Captain Park] That way.
-[soldiers] Yes, sir!
I think it's too late, my Lord.
The Murky Stream
NINE. DARK RIVER
[screams]
-[door opens]
-[Seomseom] My lady.
Oh, my lady. It's okay.
You're all right now.
You're safe. You're safe.
I had a nightmare.
A terrible nightmare.
What?
It was just a bad dream, right?
Right, Seomseom?
Right?
My lady...
[crying]
[sighs softly]
Where are we right now?
Tell me it wasn't real.
Oh, my lady...
[both crying]
And Choi's daughter?
Well, Siyul had a plan.
He hid her at his old home.
She'll be safe there.
Now we're stuck taking care
of some random girl
that fell out of the sky.
Last night...
Choi's Guild was accused of treason,
and they were all put to the sword.
What does Siyul have to do with that?
They're chasing down the rest.
The ones who got out
are being hunted like dogs.
Can you really call that living?
I don't think so.
Sounds like that family's trouble.
Oh, shit.
[sighs]
Actually, I grew up here.
You and the lady should stay here.
Thank you very much.
It's a complete mess out there.
They've issued a warrant for your arrest.
They've eyes everywhere
and it's getting worse.
So how did this happen?
I have something to show you.
Is this... This is a map.
Boss, you in there?
What have you been able to uncover?
[thuds]
This is all...
I could get out of there.
This is...
This is Chun's sword, isn't it?
[fabric rustling]
[hesitates] Where is he...
without his blade?
Well, that's the thing.
Your friend, Assistant Officer Jung...
[ominous music playing]
He's in front of the city wall.
[somber music playing]
[Captain Park] Listen carefully.
"If you find any family members
or anyone connected to the traitors,
"you must report them immediately.
"If you disobey
and are caught hiding them,
"or helping them escape or,
assisting them in any way,
"the charge is treason,
and you will likewise face decapitation."
-[indistinct chatter]
-[breath trembling]
[woman sobbing] Oh, no.
[sobbing
]
[sniffling]
-Seomseom?
-[Seomseom sniffles]
[grunts] My lady?
Are you feeling any better now?
That light outside the door...
Is that the light of dusk
or the light of dawn?
The light of dawn, my lady.
Could we open the door then?
Yes.
[music continues]
This is what Chun was fighting for?
What he was protecting?
This map was created
in preparation for war.
And according to my lord, Choi,
it could save Joseon.
I'm not asking for your help
just for my sake.
Both my father and Officer Jung
gave their lives for this.
Help us fulfill their duty.
[door opens]
What's with
all the pointless chatter, huh?
-Mudeok--
-Save your breath.
I already heard everything,
and I'm not gonna help you.
So let's just pretend I didn't
hear anything or see anything.
It's time to get out of here. Got that?
Hurry your asses on out.
Mudeok sir...
Our lives are on the line here.
We need your help. I'm begging you.
Now you're just spouting some bullshit.
You think I'm gonna risk my life
to help you?
They execute those who harbor traitors,
you know that.
How dare you call them traitors?
They were righteous people.
That's neither here
nor there, little girl.
Don't even think about settling down here
and planting roots.
The government will hear
about you, real fast.
What if...
we could come to an agreement instead?
I know you care for money.
You're not serious, are you?
Money from a Traitor's Guild
is worth shit.
It's nothing but paper.
You should find somebody else.
This is a Songbang promissory note.
Two thousand nyang for immediate use.
What the... 2,000 nyang?
That's enough to buy several houses
in the finest neighborhood.
You will never have to worry
about money again.
And also...
title deeds for a ginseng farm.
-Everything you need and more.
-Please, my lady.
This is all I have to my name.
[Walwal] My goodness...
[stutters] What an offer.
What did I say?
I told you she wouldn't
take no for an answer.
Um... Uh...
I mean, we should hear her out.
Let her finish.
If the price doesn't please you,
I will look for someone else then.
-No, hold on.
-No, wait, wait.
-Don't go.
-Hold on.
[comical music playing]
The lady should at least
let us mull it over.
What are your terms, though?
I need a boat procured.
[gasps]
Find us a boat
that'll make it to Ganghwado.
[exhales]
-[grunts]
-Go away.
Have you forgotten, my lady?
These are bandits.
Who knows what it is they're scheming?
They could take our money,
hand us over to the police bureau,
or worse.
It couldn't get worse than this.
So I don't think it matters much.
[scoffs]
The way that you made that deal
reminded me of your father.
I may not know him well, but...
the Forefinger of Mapo...
he seems trustworthy to me.
Yes.
However, the thumb's a different story.
You don't trust Mudeok?
It's difficult to tell
what his intentions are.
[grunting]
-[yells]
-[both grunting]
[both panting]
Where is the map?
Where?
Just give me three days
to find them, General.
[scoffs]
You think you have three days?
You won't have a neck
in three days.
I blocked all the exits.
Every single waterway, path, and alley.
How could a mere disgraced woman
escape all this?
Fine then.
Just keep this in mind.
If you fail,
I'll shove a bull stick down your throat.
Understand?
[ominous music playing]
[sighs wearily]
Are you saying you haven't even
laid your eyes on the map?
[trembling] My sincerest apologies,
my lord.
I think I may have overestimated you.
Judging by the way you're
handling this situation,
you don't seem to deserve to be
the general of the Left Police Bureau.
[gasps] That's not true, my lord.
Do not forget...
your neck could easily end up
on the chopping block with the traitors.
I swear I will heed your warning.
I'll engrave it in my heart.
[Lord Oh] Leave.
Lord Oh.
Yes?
The culling
of the Senior Guardian General's life
was not the sole objective.
I'm well aware, Your Highness.
In order to wrap a noose
around the Seoin's necks,
we must have a clear cause.
No longer will any of these filthy and
impure forces disrupt the court's purity.
That aside...
the assistant officer who just left...
don't you think he knows too much here?
Not to mention his conduct.
He still has some use left as a pawn.
And he is more loyal than he appears.
Don't concern yourself
with him, Your Highness.
So you say.
Is this hard for you to comprehend?
Do you burn yourself to learn fire is hot?
[sighs] Not at all.
Hesitating means we lose.
We must be two steps ahead.
By your command, I will do as you wish.
We only have one life,
so why waste it living frugally?
At the end of it, all our bodies die
before rotting to dust.
Half measures get you nowhere.
[birds chirping]
[whispers] Here.
-Keep your word.
-Of course.
[grunts]
[suspenseful music playing]
[sighs wearily]
It's tomorrow at dawn.
[grunts] The boat will set off then,
at the hour of the tiger.
Thank you for doing this.
[Mudeok] Siyul...
Yes?
If you have something to say, then...
you should say it.
It's nothing important.
Please take care of yourself.
May your life be long.
Hey...
you worried that I'm gonna die?
[chuckles]
[sighs]
Save your worry for yourselves.
[laughs]
[groans]
[sighs]
[music continues]
-[crickets chirping]
-[frogs croaking]
-[owl hooting]
-[breath trembling]
[in Manchu] The doctor...
What did he say?
The stab wound is too deep.
So he cannot tell
whether she will live or not.
Do you blame me?
You took us in and raised us.
When my sister and I lived like beasts
eating rotten food.
How could we ever blame you?
Everyone dies.
The only difference is who goes first.
-[suspenseful music playing]
-[crickets chirping]
[breathing heavily]
[breath trembling]
[Mudeok] You can bring it with you...
Go wherever you want.
I will give back
what I owe you before I do.
Have you considered
the consequences at all?
After you cause a scene
and leave us all here?
Do you think we can survive on our own?
[crying]
[Siyul] Take my letter...
and do whatever you want with it.
And I will do what I have to do.
[Mudeok] You idiot!
So we'll be stuck
eating filthy rice again,
and it'll all be thanks to you?
[breath trembling]
[mumbling]
You had something to say?
Take a seat.
Well, you see...
I know where the daughter
of the Choi Guild is hiding.
I can tell you, my lord.
What did you just say?
Right now...
she's hiding in Taeseong-ri.
In a vacant house on top of a hill.
You're certain of this?
Yes.
I'm certain.
I saw her with my own two eyes.
Curious...
Tell me, how did you figure this out?
I know the one who helped that woman hide.
A member of my own clan.
My forefinger!
He's your forefinger.
That can only mean Jang.
Yes.
[scoffs] What a daring man!
So, tell me...
Why would he hide that woman
from Choi's Guild?
By doing that, he'd be putting
his own life on the line.
The boy wants revenge.
Right now,
that's what's driving him, my lord.
Revenge, you say?
[breath trembling]
JUNG CHUN
What's this?
Was this letter
written by our late Officer Jung?
You'll want to take a look
at who it's addressed to.
That's Jang's true name, the one he hid.
Jang Siyul.
Jang Siyul and Assistant Officer Jung,
they were both from Gyeongwonjin.
When Siyul lost his mother during the war
and became an orphan,
Jung's mother took him in
and raised them like brothers.
[ominous music playing]
Those two may not have shared blood,
but they were basically family.
[bamboo creaking]
[Lee Dolgae] Yes.
This is all starting to make
much more sense to me now.
Every time he was involved,
Officer Jang made such a fuss.
I always wondered why.
How very interesting.
That's not all.
Malbok's killer, Wang Hae...
he was the one who killed Siyul's mother
during the invasion.
To make matters worse, he struck down
the man Siyul called brother.
There's no question
as to why he craves revenge.
[Lee Dolgae] What a truly amusing fate.
I'm certain of it.
If it's for the sake of vengeance,
there's nothing that can hold him back.
The daughter of the Choi family,
last night, she offered me a deal.
She said If I helped her cross the river,
then I would get a large payout.
So you're saying...
they're going to cross the river.
They'll run using the waterways.
At dawn tomorrow.
That's when they plan to go,
when the tide is at its highest.
Where will they go?
I can't say, my lord.
It was kept secret
in case someone turned them in.
Answer this.
What made you decide to turn her in?
That money was yours for the taking.
You're asking why?
I'd do anything to protect my family.
Either I turned my back on him...
or he turns his back on me.
I don't see any other options.
My lord, please protect us.
[breath trembling]
He's endangering my family.
I'm afraid they're going to get hurt
all because of this.
In the end, it seems...
life is a nightmare.
[panting]
[music continues]
[grunts] The bodies are gone,
the traitors' bodies are gone.
-We need to report this now.
-[Captain Ji] Ha!
[sinister music playing]
[panting]
If anyone seems suspicious
or tries to fight back,
you're authorized to kill them.
[breathing heavily]
[door creaks]
[Yeoju wheezing]
[both grunting]
[gurgling]
[groaning]
[wheezing]
[indistinct chatter]
Captain, there's no one.
I don't even see a single rat.
The fire is still hot,
the traitors can't have gotten too far.
Be sure to search everywhere.
What was that?
Judging by the mess, they were
determined to run away.
Do you have men
tracking the Gyeonggang River?
[Captain Ji] Captain Park is currently
on his way to the dock.
Block all the waterways.
Officer Lee,
the search area is much too big.
Get more troops from the capital, then.
-To request--
-Listen to what I'm telling you.
Gather all the scattered
troops immediately.
Cut off all escape routes.
Nobody leaves the city tonight.
I move at your command.
[soldiers shouting indistinctly]
[Captain Park] Search the area.
[Lee Dolgae] Where are they?
[Captain Park] Sir, it seems
they haven't arrived yet.
Stop them no matter what.
Make sure not a single boat
makes it out of here.
Sir. Let's go.
[Gaechun panting]
-Brother.
-[Walwal] How did it go?
The soldiers who were guarding the gates
seem to be moving.
[Walwal] It's time to leave.
Come on, come on.
The road is open. We have to go now.
Jungbok, hurry!
Lady Eun? Lady Eun?
Hurry! Come, let's hurry.
Come quickly! Quick!
Quickly, my lady.
[bandit screaming]
Brother! Brother! It's me!
[Walwal] Quickly! Come on!
Let's hurry.
[bandit groaning]
[grunting]
[bandit 2 grunts]
[yells]
[bandit 3 screams]
Keep fighting,
and I will have no choice...
but to cut you down where you stand.
[bandit 4 screams, wails]
[Wang Hae] I was wondering who it was.
You were swinging that sickle
like an animal.
[Siyul] They're waiting
for you in hell.
It's time for you to meet them.
[Wang Hae breathing heavily]
I'll claim your last breath.
In this world...
death would be a blessing.
[both scream]
[screams]
[both grunting]
[grunts, breathes heavily]
[Wang Hae yells]
[both grunting]
[Wang Hae grunts]
[grunts, breathing heavily]
[both yell]
[Siyul grunts]
How pathetic.
Did you really think you were
good enough to win this fight?
I'm going to kill you tonight.
I swear it.
[growls]
[both grunting]
[Siyul straining]
[Wang Hae groans]
[both screaming]
[both groaning, panting]
[Wang Hae yells]
[both straining]
[Wang Hae straining]
[Siyul breathing heavily]
[chokes]
[Siyul growls]
-[Wang Hae yells]
-[Siyul grunts]
[Siyul huffs]
[Wang Hae yells]
[Wang Hae straining]
Do you think the just world
you want can truly exist?
That doesn't matter now.
[Siyul grunts]
I will see you pay
for all the things you've done.
[chuckles]
A life for a life, blood for blood.
[grunts]
-[Wang Hae gurgles]
-[growls]
[♪ melancholy music playing]
[sobbing]
[continues sobbing]
[♪ melancholy music continues]
[singer vocalizing]
[rapid footsteps approaching]
[soldiers breathing heavily]
[all breathing heavily]
-Okay, this is good.
-Yeah?
[Gaechun] Oh, God, that was...
Because one rabid dog went wild...
now the rest...
are following suit.
-[shudders]
-You think I'm a fool
that you can just toy with?
You're mistaken, my lord.
That... that could never be.
You planned this, didn't you?
What could I even gain from doing that?
[shudders] That's just not possible.
I didn't know.
Admit it.
Admit that you were the one
who planned this.
It's a misunderstanding.
Or... or a mistake.
I bet Jang Siyul and that woman,
together they schemed to--
[Lee Dolgae grunts]
-[Lee Dolgae screams]
-[shudders]
What do I have to do?
Shall I gouge out your eyes
and crush them to make you tell the truth?
Where are they? Where are the bastards?
[crying] I swear on my life,
I don't know where they are.
I'm getting impatient.
Tell me.
I only turned them in as traitors.
What exactly did I do so wrong?
-Fine. I'll just slit your throat!
-[wailing]
Sir, you can't. Too many eyes here.
Rats like him will end up
dying in a ditch anyway.
-Why get his dirty blood on your blade?
-[crying]
[Lee Dolgae grunts] Less than a parasite!
After I took you in!
[Lee Dolgae grunting]
Die, you leech! Die! Die! Die!
[grunts, screams]
I swear you cross my path again,
I'll kill you.
[whimpering]
Strip him of his robes now.
[wailing]
[Eun sighs deeply]
[Chief Kang crying]
[crying]
[♪ somber music playing]
[Jungbok] Brother.
[gasps] Oh, Siyul.
[Gaechun crying]
Oh. Oh, brother. It's you.
Took you really long. Oh, thank you.
Did you do it?
[Gaechun continues crying]
[♪ somber music continues]
Your hand.
Oh, Siyul.
It must have been tough.
[Jungbok] Brother.
Your friend...
he's buried over there.
You should pay your respects.
[♪ somber music continues]
[Siyul sobs softly]
[Gaechun sniffles]
[continues sobbing]
[♪ somber music continues]
[music stops]
Ming, is it? That's where you're going?
I'll deliver the map
to the Ganghwa magistrate first.
And then I plan to cross the sea.
The journey will be difficult.
[chuckles softly]
I have Chief Kang and Seomseom.
I know I can always
rely on their strength.
I think I'll be okay.
[♪ soft instrumental music playing]
[Eun] Your hand...
it's still bleeding.
[Siyul groans softly]
Do you have somewhere else to go?
If not, perhaps you'd like to join us?
I intend to head to the border.
I guess...
this is goodbye then.
[inhales deeply]
[Chief Kang] My lady,
we have a long road ahead.
Let's hurry and say our goodbyes.
Please take care of yourself.
[♪ soft instrumental music continues]
Before I leave...
my name.
I'm Choi Eun.
Thank you.
I'll never forget your kindness.
Siyul is mine.
Jang Siyul.
Please...
you have to survive this.
[♪ soft instrumental music continues]
Were you successful tonight?
Yes. Just as you ordered.
They will follow the plan.
[♪ suspenseful music playing]
[yells]
What is this? You have a death wish?
I don't think you realize
the situation you're in.
What?
-[chuckles]
-You stubborn idiot!
You don't realize the power
of a Joseon officer.
[grunts] I'll show you then. [yells]
[grunts]
You son of a...
[groans loudly]
What the hell are you all doing?
[laughs]
How can a Police Bureau officer
be so clueless?
Can't you read the room?
[Osam laughs]
[Lee Dolgae gasps]
Now pay attention.
This is the last sight
you're ever gonna see!
[Lee Dolgae grunts]
[coughs, gurgles]
How dare you bastards!
Look at him. He just won't die.
[Gangseop] Yeah, enough of this shit.
Let's just get it over with.
[Lee Dolgae grunts]
Step out of line and this is what you get!
-[Osam yells]
-[Lee Dolgae grunts]
[gurgling]
[coughs]
[chokes]
[Dochi sighs deeply]
♪ I can't go on ♪
♪ Oh, I can't go on ♪
♪ I can't go on... ♪
[Jungbok and Walwal]
Boss! Boss! Boss!
[both panting]
[Walwal] Look at you. Goodness!
-[Jungbok] Oh, no.
-Shit!
Boss!
Oh, no, no, no. Look at his face.
Are you all right?
-[Mudeok] Hey, hey, hey!
-[all gasp]
You ungrateful shits.
You all remember what I said?
I said our boss won't go down easily.
His lifeline is long, isn't it?
-I--
-Ah, I can't believe you idiots.
How could you choose Siyul over me,
your boss? Huh?
What would you say,
how many years have we been together?
Oh, you, you, you,
you backstabbing, traitorous little...
Uh... Hey, boss.
Actually, about that...
Brother, you tell him. Go on, tell him.
-Tell him.
-Me?
Uh-huh.
What?
Well, you said...
Didn't you say it was at least
worth a try or something?
Well, Walwal just kept saying...
[mimics Walwal]
"We can't pass this, it's 2,000 nyang,"
[in normal voice] over and over again.
So I just nod along.
Is that wrong?
What are you on about?
Brother, your exact words.
"Mudeok will sell them out. No question."
Didn't he?
[Walwal] That was only because...
All right, Siyul wouldn't
stop complaining,
so that's why I... I... [stutters]
I was just playing along. Hey, quiet!
What is this nonsense?
-Get your story straight!
-[mumbles]
-Tell him.
-[exhales sharply]
[exhales sharply]
Okay, I'll tell you what happened.
This part is truly important.
Please listen carefully.
[♪ suspenseful music playing]
This evening, you must not leave
on the boat as we had planned.
-Wait. What?
-Huh?
Mudeok is going to report us
to the Police Bureau and the officials.
-I am certain of it.
-[both gasp]
That's right.
He will sell them out. No question.
[stutters] Then what now?
Look here, the Inwangsan Mountain area
has a trail.
Before this map,
we didn't know it existed.
[Siyul] This evening,
when the capital troops join the search,
we'll move to that trail.
That's the real plan.
So what you're saying is,
boss turns them in, makes it a big search.
Officers will join in on the search
and head to the port.
We'll use it to take the mountain trail.
-It'd be wide open.
-[Gaechun] Exactly.
Okay, but what about our boss, though?
What?
The aftermath? Can he handle it?
It won't be easy,
but I think he'll make it.
Oh, yeah! Look!
It's 2,000 nyang.
For that amount,
it's worth struggling a little.
Wouldn't you agree? Am I wrong?
Yeah, yeah.
It's 2,000 nyang, and also think about it.
Our boss, Mudeok, is resilient
and can survive anything.
-Isn't that right?
-Exactly.
-[Walwal] Won't die.
-[Gaechun] Right.
-[Walwal] He never dies.
-[Gaechun] Of course not.
You're right. He's invincible.
-He'd never die. Not him.
-Mm-hmm.
For fuck's sake! I swear,
you're all traitorous little shits.
You were all gonna split the money
after you sell me off, right?
No, it's just...
The meals we could eat
with that money, I could taste them.
It's 2,000 nyang. We had to do it.
Can you blame us?
Hey. That's why I turned them in,
ding-a-ling.
Oh! It was all
for your damn sakes, all right?
-You know that?
-[laughs]
That's the opposite
of what you're always saying.
Turning away from suffering
is what a bandit does.
[sighs deeply]
[man] War!
They've declared war!
Hey, everyone! Hey, they declared war!
They declared war.
-War's coming!
-[Mudeok] What's he squawking about?
-[man 2] What's he saying?
-[man] Look there!
-[villagers speaking indistinctly]
-Oh, shit.
-[Mudeok sighs]
-Wait, hold on!
-What's that over there?
-Huh?
[villagers speaking indistinctly]
[Walwal] Could it be a fire?
-[Gaechun] I think it's a smoke signal.
-[Mudeok sighs, grunts]
[Jungbok] A real war?
♪ I can't go on ♪
[Gaechun] What will happen to us now?
♪ Because of the war ♪
That's it, my lady.
Once we cross this river,
we'll reach Ganghwado.
What is that?
[Chief Kang] Wait, my lady.
Someone has lit the beacon.
[breathing heavily]
[♪ slow suspenseful music playing]
[♪ somber instrumental music playing]
[♪ music swells]
[♪ music fades]